Finding Aid for the Peter Plagens papers LSC.2255
UCLA Library Special Collections
Peter Plagens papers
1938-2014
UCLA Library Special Collections
Plagens, Peter
LSC.2255
13.4 linear feet (26 document boxes, 10 half document boxes, and 1 oversize flat box)
Peter Plagens is an abstract painter, art critic, professor and novelist based in New York City. The collection consists of art work, exhibition materials, art criticism, published and unpublished novels, correspondence, lectures, course materials, photographs, slides, notebooks, datebooks, journals, and memorabilia.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed digital materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter Plagens and Laurie Fendrich, 2014.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9975365603606533
Biography/History
Peter Plagens was born in Dayton, Ohio in 1941 but grew up in Los Angeles after his family moved when he was two years old. His parents, George and Jayne Plagens, who both worked, saved their cash to buy a small house in the city. Peter graduated from John Marshall High School, then paid his way through the University of Southern California (USC) with a partial scholarship from the university and a job at a supermarket.
He received a Bachelor's degree from the USC School of Fine Arts in 1962 and a Master of Fine Arts degree from Syracuse University in 1964. He was a recipient of a Guggenheim Fellowship in Painting and two National Endowment for the Arts Fellowships in Painting.
Plagens, an abstract painter, met fellow painter Walter Gabrielson in 1963 at USC when he returned to campus in an attempt to reclaim his undergraduate job in the Psychology Department on a research project called "BC: Analysis of Behavioral Cognition." According to Plagens, he returned to find that Gabrielson had taken his job drawing stimuli for social intelligence tests to be used by the Navy to assess the kind of crew members who could withstand confinement in submarines. The project now required two cartoonists, so Plagens began work on the project again but this time in a cubicle adjacent to Gabrielson. There they began their lifelong friendship.
In 1969 Plagens returned to Los Angeles when Gabrielson found him a teaching job in the Art Department of San Fernando Valley State College, now known as California State University, Northridge. They shared an office on campus and became known informally among art students as the "Pete 'n' Wally Show," and from 1970 they shared a 3,000 square foot studio in Pasadena until Plagens left Northridge in 1978.
Plagens has exhibited his work at the Nancy Hoffman Gallery in New York City for over 40 years, and his paintings are part of the permanent collections of many museums and corporations, including the Baltimore Museum of Art, Chase Manhattan Bank, the Hirschhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden in Washington D.C., and the Museum of Contemporary Art in San Diego, California. Plagens' art has been the subject of numerous solo exhibitions in galleries and museums such as the USC Fisher Gallery, the Akron Art Museum, the Las Vegas Art Museum and Texas Gallery, Houston.
According to Plagens' wife, painter Laurie Fendrich, Peter fell into writing art criticism but he also enjoys it. His first review appeared in Artforum in 1966. His writing has appeared in a multitude of publications including Art in America, Art News, The Chronicle of Higher Education, American Art and The Wall Street Journal. However, Plagens may be best known as the art critic and senior writer for Newsweek magazine between 1989 and 2003.
Plagens has taught at Middlebury College in Vermont, Hofstra University in New York, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, where he also chaired the art department, California State University at Northridge, USC, the University of California at Berkeley, and the University of Texas at Austin. Notably, in 1998 Plagens was one of four senior fellows in the National Arts Journalism Program at Columbia University.
In addition to his work as an artist and educator, Plagens is also the author of five books: Sunshine Muse: Contemporary Art on the West Coast (1974), Moonlight Blues: An Artist's Art Criticism (1986), Time for Robo (1999), Sunshine Muse: Modern Art on the West Coast 1945-1970 (2000), The Art Critic (2008 and 2012), and Bruce Nauman: The True Artist (2014).
Plagens works and lives in New York City with his wife, Laurie Fendrich.
Scope and Content
The Peter Plagens papers consist of art work, exhibition materials, art criticism, published and unpublished novels, correspondence, lectures, course materials, photographs, slides, notebooks, datebooks, journals and memorabilia, ranging in date from 1938 to 2014.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Art Work
Series 2: Exhibition Materials
Series 3: Writing
Series 4: Correspondence
Series 5: Lectures
Series 6: Course Materials
Series 7: Photos and Slides
Series 8: Notebooks and Datebooks
Series 9: DRIPS
Series 10: Memorabilia
Related Material
Walter Gabrielson papers (Collection 1830). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Interview of Peter Plagens [oral history transcript] / Kavior Moon, interviewer. UCLA Library Special Collections, Center for Oral History Research interview, 2017. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Art critics -- United States -- Archives.; Painters -- United States -- Archives.; Novelists, American -- 20th century -- Archives.
- Art Work, 1958-2011
  Scope and Content
  This series includes drawings, a poster created with artist Walter Gabrielson, art work ledgers, a hard drive with digital images of art work and slides of his paintings and collages. Plagens' slide numbering system involves sequential numbers for each work before the hyphen and the year the work was made follows the hyphen. For example, 32-99 refers to the 32nd work produced in 1999.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - DT cartoons, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Photocopies of cartoons Plagens created while working as an editorial cartoonist for the University of Southern California (USC) Daily Trojan student newspaper cover a range from campus issues (e.g. criticism of the Doheny Library) to national issues (e.g. academic freedom and army recruitment) to international politics (e.g communism and U.S. relations with Cuba).
  - Richard de Mille drawing, circa 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Drawing of de Mille wearing a Trojan helmet and GOP necklace, created by Plagens while he and Walter Gabrielson worked as staff artists for a USC Psychology Department research project called "BC: Analysis of Behavioral Cognition." Gabrielson and Plagens were each assigned to work for a particular researcher. Plagens was assigned to work for Richard de Mille, adopted son of Cecil B. de Mille. The sword and sandals movie motif and Grand Old Party necklace are references to Richard's father, Cecil. During this project, Gabrielson and Plagens would create humorous drawings, fold them as paper airplanes and fly them over the partition into each other's cubicles.
  - "Who Wrote The Note?" Contest flyer, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Plagens made this flyer while a graduate student at Syracuse University. Syracuse assigned semi-private studios to its studio grad students on the second floor of an old Continental Can Company. An art history graduate student named Patricia Amlin received a large studio space and posted a log of all her studio hours. When Plagens and his pals began to fill in impossible hours on Amlin's log, she became furious and demanded to know who was responsible. Plagens created this flyer as a response. The caricatures of the artists depicted on the flyer are as follows: 1) Bob Conge 2) Richard Jordan 3) Michael Ashcraft 4) Peter Plagens, and 5) Gerry DiGiusto.
  - Plagens slides, 1958-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Slides include images of oil paintings Plagens created as an undergraduate at USC and as a graduate student at Syracuse University, the Pasadena studio he shared with Walter Gabrielson, his solo exhibition at the University of Oklahoma Art Museum, his "Confessions of a Fellatrix" installation, and his Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art (LAICA) downtown installation. Materials also include images of art in Brussels, Amsterdam and London as well as natural scenes in Austin, Texas and Oregon.
  - Plagens art slides, 1980-2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Slides include images from his solo exhibition, "Intimate Dramas: Peter Plagens' Black Paintings" at the Akron Art Museum and works such as Brotherhood of Artists, Basketball in Hollywood, Noam Sain (Time for Robo), Jehova's Waitress, The Last Modernist, and The Red & The Black: Said Satan.
  - Plagens small collages slides, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    Materials include more than 500 slides of Plagens' small collages.
  - Peter Plagens art slides, 1961-2002 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    Materials include mixed media collages such as Brotherhood of Artists, Dark Matisse Flame, Queen of the Blues and Richter as a Painter, However.
  - School and Jan Baum Gallery slides, 1960-1963, 1979-1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Slides include images of Plagens' work from the Abstract Artists' Exhibition at the Jan Baum Gallery located at 170 South La Brea Avenue in Los Angeles.
  - Peter Plagens art slides, 1975-1982, 1993-1994, 1997, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
    Materials include more than a thousand slides and the following transparencies: Cleveland Defaults On Its Debts, An Obvious Heterosexual and Have You Ever Seriously Considered A Monarchy?
  - Peter Plagens: Slides of student work, 1969, 1973-1975, 1977-1980, 1983-1984, 1988, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    More than four hundred slides of student work from Beginning Drawing, Beginning Painting, Advanced Painting and Independent Study courses taught by Plagens.
  - Collages I-III slides, 1972-1976, 1984-1989 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
    Approximately nine hundred slides of Plagens' collages.
  - Ledgers of work, 1972-1975, 1976-1981, 1982-1987, 1987-1991, 1992-2002 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
    Five handwritten ledgers of Plagens' art work are numbered 1-5, arranged in chronological order and signed by the artist. Although started in 1972, the first book includes his work from the 1960s and in addition to photographs and sketches of his work, all books record dates, serial numbers, storage locations, materials, dimensions, titles, sales, gifts, damage and destruction.
  - Studio, circa 1996-1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Materials include painting title ideas and photographs used for Plagens's art work. One photo was taken at the 1934 Air Show at the Cleveland Municipal Airport. The image is of Plagens's father, George Plagens, single at age 26 in a suit and tie and his brother, Harold at age 18 wearing his East High football sweater. Peter made three drawings from this photograph. He sold the best one, gave his daughter Sybil Wisdom the second one, and he kept the third.
  - Art inventory and exhibition floppy disks, 1965-1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Materials include 4 art inventory floppy disks.
    Four 3.5-inch floppy disks
    Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Art work CDs, 1974-2009, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Nine CDs contain images of Plagens' work with the following titles: Collages 1974-2000 (selected), Collage Survey 1974-2000 (selected), Peter's Work (dupe), Plagens' "Introspective" at Columbia College 2005, Peter Plagens' Art/Images September 2006, Peter's Work September 15, 2006, Peter Plagens' 5 Works on Paper 2007 (draft), Peter Plagens' Images 1974-2009 and Peter Plagens' Collage-Paintings 2011.
    9 CDs
  - Hard drive, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    One iomega Helium portable hard drive contains images of Plagens' art work.
    1 hard drive
  - Floppy disks (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Seven 3.5" floppy disks
  - BIG LIE Smash It! poster, circa 1970s (Box 36, Folder 4)
    Anti-war protest poster created by Plagens and Walter Gabrielson.
  - Life Map, 2006 March 22 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    This flowchart style map was drawn by Plagens with black and red pencil.
  - Untitled, circa 2010 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    Plagens created this colored abstract drawing and tore it off from a Walker's NYC restaurant tablecloth. Walker's is Plagens' and Fendrich's neighborhood restaurant in Tribeca that places glasses filled with crayons on their dining tables. Plagens estimates that they have eaten there over 600 times in 30 years.
- Exhibition Materials, 1967-2013
  This series includes posters, catalogues, brochures, invitations, postcards and a floppy disk concerning Plagens' solo and group exhibitions in addition to catalogues with essays by Plagens and brochures for exhibitions curated by Plagens. This series also includes Plagens' Funny Guys proposal for a Walter Gabrielson and Merwin Belin exhibition and curatorial texts annotated by Plagens.
  - Smagula and Plagens posters, 1967 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    Four posters publicize Plagens' exhibition with Howard Smagula at the New Arts Gallery in Houston, Texas.
  - Confessions of a Fellatrix (paintings) posters, 1971 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    Three posters promote Plagens' solo show at 16 West Union Street in Pasadena, California.
  - 24 Young Los Angeles Artists LACMA handout, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    This Los Angeles County Museum of Art (LACMA) photographic handout for an exhibition of young, local artists features Plagens on the cover.
  - Peter Plagens: Works On Paper catalogue, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Catalogue for Plagens' exhibition at the Smithsonian's Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden.
  - Peter Plagens: Visiting Artist Program posters, 1978 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    Three posters for the Wake Forest University/Southeastern Center for Contemporary Art (SECCA) Visiting Artist Program feature an exhibition of Plagens's paintings and the following two artist lectures: "The State of Painting on the West Coast" and "My Work." The back of one poster includes a family portrait in crayon by Plagens and Joyce Wisdom's daughter Sybil Wisdom.
  - Peter Plagens: Selected Small Works postcards, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Three opening reception postcards for Plagens' exhibition at the Los Angeles Harbor College Fine Arts Gallery.
  - Eaton Fine Art 10th Anniversary catalogue, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    This catalogue includes a "Best Wishes for the New Year" note from Timothy A. Eaton and features Peter Plagens and Laurie Fendrich's "Artists & Writers/Husbands & Wives" group exhibition as a highlight.
  - Peter Plagens: An Introspective opening invitation, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Invitation to the opening reception for Plagens' solo exhibition at USC Fisher Gallery, addressed to Director and Curator Selma Holo.
  - Peter Plagens: An Introspective brochures, 2004-2005 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Three brochures for his solo exhibition at USC Fisher Gallery feature a color reproduction of Plagens' Benton Way and Sunset, LA, 6/28/55, 1:40p.m. work on the cover and include a biography of the artist and descriptions of his early and late work.
  - Peter Plagens: An Introspective catalogues, 2004-2005 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    These two catalogues feature acknowledgements from USC Fisher Gallery Director and Curator Selma Holo, a transcription of a conversation between Holo and Plagens, "The Jabberwocky and the Gorilla in the Corner" essay by MacArthur Prize Winner Dave Hickey, Afterword by The Butler Institute of American Art Executive Director Louis A. Zona and full color plates of Plagens' work.
  - Peter Plagens: An Introspective mailers, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Three publicity mailer cards announce the dates of the exhibition, its opening reception and artist lecture at the A + D 11th Street Gallery in Chicago, Illinois. Plagens' Wheels of Wonder is featured in full color as the cover image.
  - "Paint & Tell" article, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    This article was published in the summer issue of the USC Trojan Family magazine. Plagens, who was interviewed for this feature, discusses his work with a focus on his exhibition at USC Fisher Gallery, which showcased 44 pieces spanning 30 years of his artistic career. According to the author of the article, this was the first time the museum held a solo show dedicated to the art work of an alumnus.
  - Peter Plagens Reception for Artist cards, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Two Reception for Artist cards for Plagens' solo exhibition at the Nancy Hoffman Gallery feature a full color view of his studio.
  - Peter Plagens: An Introspective reception cards, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Three cards for his reception at The Butler Institute of American Art include statements from the Director and Chief Curator Louis A. Zona on the importance of Plagens' work.
  - Driven to Abstraction... catalogue, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    The Driven to Abstraction: Southern California and the Non-Objective World, 1950-1980 catalogue was produced for the Riverside Art Museum's historical survey exhibition curated by Peter Frank. This exhibition featured Plagens' work, The People's Republic of Antarctica, an image of which is found on page 77 of the catalogue.
  - Ron Linden catalogues, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Two catalogues for painter Ron Linden's exhibition at Cue Art Foundation in New York include an artist's statement, curator's statement, and full color images of Linden's work. The exhibition, curated by Plagens, was Linden's first solo show in New York. This folder also includes letters from Linden to Plagens concerning the choice of work for the catalogue cover and correspondence from Cue Art Foundation Programs Assistant Ryan White regarding the exhibition and its opening reception.
  - Truckscapes: Drawings from a Mobile Studio book, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    This book of Nick Miller's landscape drawings includes an essay by Plagens entitled, "Nick Miller: Drawing Life from Landscape." This publication serves as documentation of Miller's solo exhibition of the same name at the Irish Cultural Center in Paris.
  - Funny Guys proposal, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Plagens' notes concerning his Walter Gabrielson and Merwin Belin exhibition proposal, Gabrielson press clippings and work photos, a transparency of Belin's work, and a Merwin Belin Professional NBC Sports 1992 Summer Olympics Barcelona luggage tag.
  - Mississippi Invitational catalogue, 2009 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Plagens served as Guest Curator for this exhibition at the Mississippi Museum of Art and his catalogue essay, "The Deep (as in Profound) South" discusses studio visits and the work of the ten artists he chose to participate in this show.
  - Painting with Paint brochures, 2010 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Two brochures for the Painting with Paint: Selections from the Nancy Hoffman Gallery exhibition that featured works by Plagens, Howard Buchwald, Hung Liu and Joseph Raffael, include an image of Plagens' Serge Protector piece alongside text he wrote concerning the appeal of abstraction in connection with the existential truth of painting.
  - School of Belin catalogue, 2010 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    This catalogue for the Merwin Belin exhibition, School of Belin: A Mid-Career Survey at the Warschaw Gallery in San Pedro includes an essay by Plagens on Belin's life and work.
  - Peter Plagens: I Don't Give a Damn / Every Moment Counts cards, 2011 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    Two reception invitation cards for Plagens' solo exhibition at the Nancy Hoffman Gallery feature an image of Plagens' 2010 work by the same name.
  - Thinking Contemporary Curating publication, 2012 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    Publication by Terry Smith, first in a series developed by Independent Curators International (ICI) entitled, Perspectives in Curating. This copy is heavily annotated by Plagens.
  - The Culture of Curating and the Curating of Culture(s) proof, 2012 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    Uncorrected page proof of publication by Paul O'Neil, annotated throughout by Plagens.
  - Abstract, adj.: Expressing a quality apart from an object. brochure, 2013 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    This brochure for the group exhibition at the Ringling College of Art and Design Selby Gallery features Plagens' Get In There Fast work on the cover.
  - Peter Plagens Texas Gallery opening brochures, 2013 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    Three brochures for Plagens' solo exhibition at the Texas Gallery in Houston feature full color images of the following works: The Italian Job 3, Death of an Artist 1, Impure Abstraction Notes from the Underground 3, The Crust of Life 2 and The Case for Abstraction 3.
  - Peter Plagens Exhibition floppy disk, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
    This floppy disk includes "lo-fi" digital photos of Plagens' work for the purpose of documentation.
    One 3.5-inch floppy disk
- Writing, 1970-2012
  This series includes Plagens' reviews and articles for Newsweek, Art in America, Artforum and other publications, his West Coast Art manuscript, Sunshine Muse photographs and illustration releases, notes and drafts of his first novel, Time for Robo, drafts of his second novel, The Art Critic, research, notes and drafts for his Bruce Nauman: The True Artist book, and multiple drafts of the following unpublished works of fiction: Robo 2: Noam Sain and the Altadena Bungalow, Robo 3: Among Those Killed in the Dawn Raid Was the Reverend Noam Sain, Aged One Hundred, Merciful Brief, Lieutenant Kao and Confessions of a Fellatrix.
  - Art Writing Old, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Materials include an article for Artforum in which Plagens discusses Richard Serra's Sawing as a "bona fide sensation."
  - Art Writing Muy Viejo, 1970-1971, circa 1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Materials include an essay for Art Journal entitled "Some Problems in Recent Painting" and two photocopies of the following typescripts: "Me 'N The Scene" and "True Garb."
  - "The Odd Couple" review, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Plagens discusses the work of Jim Turrell and Walter Gabrielson in this New West article.
  - "Golden Days" essay, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Plagens discusses contemporary art in Los Angeles in this essay clipped from the book, Modern Art and Popular Culture: Readings in High and Low.
  - Art Writing - Misc., 1993-1997 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    Materials include an essay on Doug Hilson for his exhibition at the Laura Knott Art Gallery, a profile on Ron Linden, a review of The San Francisco School of Abstract Expressionism show organized by the Laguna Art Museum, an interview of artist and former Artforum editor, John Coplans, and a typescript on the work of painter Sam Francis.
  - Art Writing - Misc., 1998-1999, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Materials include an article on the L.A. art scene for the Los Angeles Times, an annotated list of the "ten best art thingies of the '90s" for Artforum, selections from "Art Stripped Bare," Plagens' collaboration with Walter Gabrielson and a "Bring Back 'Amos 'n' Andy,' but With Care" article for The Chronicle of Higher Education.
  - Art Writing - Misc., 2000-2003 (Box 8, Folder 8)